<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Gangrænachrestum, or A plaister to alay the tumor, and prevent the spreading of a pernitious vlcer, like to have grown upon, and putrified the good report of Jo. Maddocks, and Henry Pinnell. Made up of a true relation (wherein the faults of the former impression by Master Edwards are revised, corrected, and amended) concerning some passages at Pool. / By the abused parties I.M. and H.P.</title>
            <author>Maddocks, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 69 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89229</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M246</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E353_12</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201080</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861648</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861648</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113788</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89229)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113788)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 57:E353[12])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Gangrænachrestum, or A plaister to alay the tumor, and prevent the spreading of a pernitious vlcer, like to have grown upon, and putrified the good report of Jo. Maddocks, and Henry Pinnell. Made up of a true relation (wherein the faults of the former impression by Master Edwards are revised, corrected, and amended) concerning some passages at Pool. / By the abused parties I.M. and H.P.</title>
                  <author>Maddocks, John.</author>
                  <author>Pinnell, Henry.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 29, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[H. Hall],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare 1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Thomason notes that it is London printing, .. But for once he is wrong: it is real Oxford printing by Henry Hall"--Madan.</note>
                  <note>A reply to: Edwards, Thomas. Gangræna.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "London Sept: 5th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Edwards, Thomas, 1599-1647. --  Gangræna --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Preaching --  legal status, laws, etc. --  Early works to 1800</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113788:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Gangraenachreſtum,</hi> OR, A PLAISTER TO ALAY THE tumor, and prevent the ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of a pernitious Vlcer, like to have growne upon, and putrified the good report of JO. MADDOCKS, and HENRY PINNELL.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Made up of a true Relation (wherein the faults of the former Impreſsion by Maſter</hi> Edwards are reviſed, corrected, and amended) concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſome paſſages at POOL.</p>
            <p>By the abuſed parties <hi>I. M.</hi> and <hi>H. P.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal. 56.5.</hi>
                  </bibl> Every day they wreſt my words: all their thoughts are againſt mee for evill.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal. 63.11.</hi>
                  </bibl> The mouth of them that speake lies ſhall be ſtopped.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Prov. 3.29.</hi>
                  </bibl> Deviſe not evill againſt thy neighbour ſeeing he dwelleth ſecurely by thee.</p>
               <l>
                  <hi>Accuſamus ſaepè quod nos facimus; Deſertè in aliorum vitia invehimur.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cum tua praevideas oculis mala lippus inunctis,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cur in amicorum vitiis tam cernis acutìm?</hi>
               </l>
               <bibl>Horat.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed in the yeare 1646.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:113788:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113788:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE enſuing narration of my Brother was directed to me ſome moneths ſince; but by reaſon of the great diſtance betweene him and me, and my unſetledneſſe of habitation, it came to my hands but very lately, elſe thou hadſt ſeene it ſooner; though I am ſorry thou haſt the ſight of it (or mine) at all; in this reſpect, that I feare the <hi>diviſions of Reuben</hi> may encreaſe the thoughts of thy heart: Not that I deſire to ſcatter in Iſrael, or divide in Jacob, <hi>we to him by whom offences come; would to God they were cut off that trouble thee:</hi> my purpoſe is rather to compoſe and unite: to that end I here offer this piece of <hi>truth</hi> to make up the breach made by the <hi>untruths</hi> of Maſter <hi>Edwards,</hi> and his buſie Pettifoggers. In one of his Canonicall Epiſtles (for he thinkes <hi>Gangrana</hi> is authenticke) there thou ſhalt find Maſter <hi>Maddocks</hi> and my ſelfe with a viper on our hands;
<note place="margin">Act. 28.1, 2, 3, 4.</note> ſome mens bookes are like the Iland of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lita,</hi> abounding with ſuch kind of venemous creatures. And though the barbarous people may expect our ſwelling and ſinking, the downefall and ruine of our reputation, by the poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning of our name and credit; yet I doubt not but to ſhake off this banefull beaſt without any loſſe of life, or hurt of health at all. I once thought to have ſpread a bigger plaiſter for my owne ſore; but ſince my brothers ſalve is enough for his owne wound and mine, I ſhall contract; but ſome anſwer muſt be put into this infamous Declaration, leſt the <hi>Knights of the Poſt</hi> be impannell'd, and I found guilty of the heinous crime laid
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113788:3"/>againſt mee. Reader, thou ſhalt be judge and I will open the matter before thee as truly as if I had kiſſed the Booke.</p>
            <p>When the ſeige lay before <hi>Sherbourne</hi> Caſtle in <hi>Dorſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> I went to ſee <hi>Poole;</hi> where (by the importunity of ſome freinds) I preached, <hi>Auguſt</hi> 8. 1645. Captaine <hi>Throttle,</hi> ſometime a Parſon, Vicar or Curate, was offended at my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, pretending that blaſphemy which <hi>S. F.</hi> takes for grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be true, and confidently commends it to a Credulous, Claſſicall, Canonicall Church-man as a conſiderable ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for the Gangraemiſt to make up his tumifying volume.</p>
            <p>But that thou mayeſt know the certaintie of thoſe things whereof thou haſt beene miſ-inform'd, and that it may appeare the offence was taken, through the miſtaking of Captaine <hi>Throttle,</hi> and not given by my diſcourſe, I ſhall recite onely that paſſage of his groundleſſe exception, laying it at thy feet and leaving it before the barre.</p>
            <p>Having occaſion to ſpeake of the body of ſin and death, as the great hindrance of the Saints comfort, and withall hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth their remedy and recovery by Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Rom. 7.</note> I brought in <hi>Paul</hi> perſonating a ſad ſoule in a diſtreſſed condition <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.14, 15, 24. and then propoſed him as a patterne of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyceing upon his ground, <hi>v.</hi> 25. I ſay (as then I did) that the children of God in the Ecclipſe of Chriſt may complaine of that in themſelves (<hi>i.</hi>) the body of ſin and death from which they are delivered by Chriſt, in reſpect of their juſtification, of which I then ſpake and wherewith I bounded that part of my diſcourſe; and did the Saints allwayes remember their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance from ſin by Jeſus Chriſt they would not have that cauſe of complaining in them, which otherwiſe they will have ariſeing from, and tending to the bondage of their ſpirits. I endeavoured to illuſtrate the thing and explaine my meaning by a paralell ſcripture.
<note place="margin">Pſalm. 43.</note> 
               <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 43.5. when the ſoule doth act upon, and truſt in the goodneſſe and grace of God by faith in Chriſt then it is free from diſquietneſſe: the utmoſt of my folly was, to prove <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> to have but one lippe and ſpeake the ſame language, which is common to the Saints, this is the <hi>weakeneſſe</hi> wherewith I charged <hi>Paul.</hi> Truely I never
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113788:3"/>denyed that <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 3.23. Eph. 2.3.</note> or any other Saint had a body of ſinne about them; but in the handling the ſame particular I proved all the ſonnes and daughters of <hi>Adam</hi> to be ſinners, and to have need of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Reader I expoſe my ſelfe to thy cenſure. Say, whether (having granted all men to be ſinners in <hi>Adam,</hi> and conclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the old man to be a great hinderer of the Saints comfort and peace) thou thinkeſt I ſhould (in the ſame breath) deny a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch thing as a body of ſinne and death to be in the godly, in any ſenſe: but if thou imputeſt miſtake or forgetfullneſſe to me, yet I have another ſtring to my bow. Maſter <hi>Bromhill,</hi> a preacher then in <hi>Poole,</hi> who tooke the notes of my Sermon, and afterward ſearched them, beare me witneſſe before many witneſſes that he found no ſuch thing either in his memory or notes. He deſired me then to give Captaine <hi>Throttle</hi> a meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in private, which I conſented unto; the place appointed was at Maſter <hi>Gundrye's</hi> houſe who was then Preacher at <hi>Dorcheſter;</hi> there I ſtaid waiting his comming to give him ſatisfaction in a loving and Chriſtian-like way; Maſter <hi>Brom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill</hi> (after long delay) went to him, but could not prevaile to bring him; then I declared my utter deteſtation of that hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid blaſphemy, of which I am accuſed, in the preſence of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Gundrye</hi> and Maſter <hi>Huſſey,</hi> both of them Preachers and ſober minded men. All this would not ſuffice; the urgency of freinds prevailed with me to preach againe the next day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sabboth-day, that I might give publicke ſatisfaction; then I openly in the Pulpit diſclaim'd that new borne blaſphemy batched in Captaine <hi>Throttle's</hi> fancy; nor will I ever owne the brats of other mens braines. I told the people alſo that I was reſolved not to turne my backe upon their Towne till I had given and received ſome ſatisfaction concerning this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: on the morrow I expected againe, &amp; ſought an opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to conferre with this Commander, but could not obtaine it; but the next day when I was taking my leave of the Major of the Towne, he comes in with ſtrange jealouſies and ſuſpicions of mid-night preaching and Sacraments, which I never ſo much as dream't of, but was as ignorant of ſuch doings in <hi>Poole</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:113788:4"/>as of the blaſphemy he charged me with. But when he could not lay his <hi>chaines</hi> upon me in <hi>Poole,</hi> he breathed out high comminations what he would doe with me in Parliament; where he durſt not ſhew his face for his eares (for you know how they deale with forgers) nor appeare in this matter.</p>
            <p>Thus farre I have clear'd my ſelfe by two witneſſes. But if my memory ſhould faile or be rejected as invalid, and ſo my firſt evidence be put by; or if Maſter <hi>Bromhill</hi> ſhould be as falſe-hearted and as double-tongu'd an hypocrite in this caſe, as he was betweene Maſter <hi>Butler</hi> and me when I ſhould have preached at <hi>Warum,</hi> and ſo my ſecond witneſſe miſcarry; yet I have a <hi>cloud</hi> of witneſſes left to make up a third teſtimony to cleare me from that foule crime of blaſphemy, ſuch as will not vaniſh nor melt away before the brighteſt Sunne of juſtice; there be ſeven and twenty men and women of honeſt report whom I can produce, who have given their names to witneſſe the contrary of what my accuſer invented And yet I have greater witneſſes then theſe; God and his Elect Angels will one day appeare for my juſtification.</p>
            <p>Thus then the Gangraene gathers,
<note place="margin">Jer: 18.18.</note> Captaine <hi>Throttle</hi> devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth a deviſe and <hi>ſmiteth with the tongue. S. F.</hi> heares the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour and buſters with his pen; <hi>Bayard</hi> is as bold with his heeles as any in the teame. There be two ſorts of men that deales their blowes as fortune doth her favours, with a blinde eye and a careleſſe hand.
<note place="margin">Jer: 20.10.</note> 
               <hi>Report</hi> (ſay they) and <hi>we will report,</hi> come on't what will; though they are forbidden ſo to do <hi>Ex.</hi> 23.1. that <hi>Facilefidian</hi> and over credulous popularity in <hi>Italy</hi> preſently fall foule on thoſe innocent and harmeleſſe <hi>Hugonites</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> if their Preiſts, Fryers, and Ghoſtly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers but once <hi>biſſe</hi> and clap their hands at them. How eaſie is it for a <hi>Synedrium,</hi> a Conventicle, Seſſion or Aſſembly of High-preiſts and Elders to perſwade the Common People to Vote Chriſt to the Croſſe when they have procured falſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe againſt him? The Convocation at Poole may happily have as ſtrong an influence upon the vulgar in thoſe parts. I know not what ſhould be the intent of <hi>S. F.</hi> when he went to put upon me that purple ſin of blaſphemy, which the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113788:4"/>had lately plunder'd in <hi>Abyſſo,</hi> where ſuch robes are wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, unleſſe it were to make the people ſpit in my face and ſet their fiſts about my eares; a better man then I was ſerv'd thus before me; I ſhall not thinke it ſtrange to be called Beel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zebub the next time. Whatever his deſigne was I weigh not, but ſure I am he told too loud a lye when he did (interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively) call me Anabaptiſt. Let him aske freind or foe, with whom I have diſcourſed about the point of baptiſme, and they will all ſay his pen run before his wit. But let his <hi>paper-wing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> meſſenger flie as faſt as it can (with the newes as light as it ſelfe), it cannot come before it is welcome to the Confederate at Ludgate-hill, Maſter <hi>Gowers,</hi> (if I ſpell his name right) who preſently, inſtead of going his rode way to the Aſſembly, ſteps aſide (I wiſh he did not wrench his foote nor wrong his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience) to caſt this <hi>mite</hi> into Maſter <hi>Edwards</hi> his <hi>Treaſury.</hi> I doubt be was ſtung when he put his finger into the Waſpes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt. But 'tis no ſtrange thing for one to loſe his way in theſe darke dayes, eſpecially grave men that grow dimme ſighted. There be that are called Seers, who yet are ſo blinde that they grope as in the night and cannot finde the right doore. I wiſh that this learned Rabbi had ſhewed the ſcribled paper to that ſolemne Aſſembly, whoſe learning and gravity I reverence, before whom ſomebody threatned to make me give an account of my doctrine, which I ſhall not refuſe to doe; that ſo he might have call'd me in as a brother before he had ſet his Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paritor to deale with me as a Publican. For I am perſwaded the wiſe men of the Synod would have debated the buſineſſe and reaſoned the caſe with him; they would (it may be) have que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned the validity of his <hi>ſingle</hi> teſtimony, and told him that he ought not to take up an evill report upon ſo ſleight a ground; that he ſhould do as he would be done by;
<note place="margin">Act: 25.16 <hi>Qus aliquid Statuerit, alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rá inaudita par. te &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> that 'tis againſt the Roman cuſtome to condemne before tryall; that to <hi>ſhut one care</hi> deſtroyes the principles of Morality and civill Juſtice; that a man (though an heretick) is not to be rejected till after firſt or ſecond admonition; that the Church is firſt to be acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the failings of the Saints, and endeavour their refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, before the world heare of them; that we are not to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113788:5"/>take up our brothers skirt but to cover his nakedneſſe with the lapp of our owne garment; <hi>doing all our things in love:</hi> Such leſſons as theſe I hope he learnes there, or elſe I ſhall thinke the worſe of the Presbyterian way as long as I know it. I ſhall leave this in Maſter <hi>Gowers</hi> his ſtudy; if he pleaſe he may take it along with him to the Convent and have it put to the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion at their next ſitting, whether his carriage to me were according to that reformation which they intend?</p>
            <p>When I went to Maſter <hi>Edwards</hi> for ſatisfaction I could get little or none at all of him, he confeſſed he never knew me, nor ever ſo much as heard of me but by that Letter of <hi>S.F.</hi> of whom (by his own confeſſion to me) he was as ignorant as of my ſelfe; and therefore he might have ſuſpected him as well as me; but becauſe one of the <hi>Presbytery</hi> had laid his hands on it, and it was brought to him by Maſter <hi>Gowers,</hi> it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately ordain'd infallible, and became <hi>worthy of all accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to him.</hi> But ſince he doth perſecute Ignorantly, (through too much beleife) not knowing the perſons on whom the ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſtrokes of his falſe tongue doe fall, the <hi>Lord lay not this ſin to his charge, but grant that he may obtaine mercy unto repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</hi> 'Tis high time he call for the prayers of the Church; for he is dangerouſly ſicke of a Gangraene, and is farre ſpent; I wiſh he die not of that diſeaſe. There is great, feare that the worſt is not paſt with him yet; for <hi>aliquid latet,</hi> the cauſe (at leaſt ſupervenient and accidentall) is not removed nor diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered: there is ſomewhat got within that feſters, though the intralls were not found before; the Gangraene hath a core at bottome; there be <hi>Canker wormes</hi> lye too neare his heart which feed the malady and foment his diſtemper, putting him ſo oft into his burning fits; he feedes upon the Letters and words of <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Philetus;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim: 2.17.</note> there's no likelyhood it ſhould goe well with him till he obſerve a better dyet. He is ſo in love with <hi>devouring words,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalm. 52.4.</note> and hath ſuck'd ſo long at the Hornets hony-combe that he hath got a <hi>bliſter</hi> upon his falſe tongue, which is ſwolne ſo bigge that he cannot keepe it within the compaſſe of his mouth: his greife muſt needes grow upon him ſo long as he foſters it with unwholſome fare;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113788:5"/>till the malignant humours be baniſhed his bowels, and driven out of his inward parts; till his heart be fortified againſt rotten inventions, and his eares ſtopp'd to keepe out the venome of a back-biting tongue, I cannot expect that the rage of his rankling ulcer ſhould abate, nor hope to ſee him reſtor'd to perfect health.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> His wound is incurable any other way then by cutting it off with the Spirits ſword of lenity and love. They which have done him much hurt are an hetero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox, heterogeneous, hereticall generation of men which have ſwarved from the right end of the Commandements (1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6.) ſuch as make pſeudaevangelicall concluſions againſt their neighbours from Traditionall premiſes: a ſuperſtitious ſort of men, a factious <hi>ſect</hi> they are; given to popery and bringing in popiſh innovations; hanging their faith upon other mens lips; making the rumour of the world the rule of their cenſure; pragmaticall whiſperers, devoted to diviſion; ſhoot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their poiſoned arrowes in ſecret to diſturbe the quiet of <hi>Iſrael; Anti-Covenanters,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 64.4.</note> not endeavouring the peace of the Kingdome wherein they live; you may call them <hi>Tradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers,</hi> or <hi>Reporters;</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. F. let. in Gang.</note> their name lurks in the ſame Font where I was baptized an Anabaptiſt: Maſter <hi>Edwards</hi> may regiſter them in his <hi>Legend,</hi> if he pleaſe, to lengthen his Catullian Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue, and patch up his <hi>Cinaedean</hi> and ſcurrilous pamphlets; unleſſe he judge them as <hi>ſupernumerary Sybils.</hi> They are a very proper potion for his thinne and empty bulke; for theſe arane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſpider-like ingredients will make his bufonius booke ſwell to a body of the greateſt magnitude. All the feare is leſt he take too great a quantity, and ſo it be with him in his ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling moode as it was with that little high-minded creature which thought to riſe above the oxe in bigneſſe: and this is much to be doubted, unleſſe he be like <hi>Mithridates</hi> to whom poiſon, was familiar; or that little ugly thing which ſome Gentlewomen uſe to tye with a chaine in the chimney corner, whoſe diſtemper'd ſtomacke will not be ſetled till it hath eaten a ſpider.
<note place="margin">Ebrius &amp; pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulans quid nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum, &amp;c.</note> Some men are ſo petulant and drunke with paſſion and envy that they ſtand in a <hi>white ſheete</hi> till they have cloathed others in <hi>purple</hi> or <hi>blacke;</hi> miſcheife and ruine of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113788:6"/>their neighbours good name is the Opium or Poppy that gives their temples reſt. You may gueſſe at Maſter <hi>Edwards</hi> his diet and conſtitution by his complexion, and ſo long as his queaſy pen no better digeſteth thoſe crude, raw and incocted informations, no mervaile if you reade his ſickneſſe in his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, as you may the ſubſtance of his booke in the front of it.</p>
            <p>My thoughts were once to have ſet up the <hi>wispe,</hi> and ſate downe in ſilence; but leſt <hi>Gangraena</hi> ſhould ſoare with her borrowed and ſtolen feathers to the like pitch of ſelfe-concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedneſſe and oſtentation, with the Antapology, I have laid this ſhackle of truth on it to hinder it from mounting aloft into that ſwelling vanity unto which it is ſo naturally addicted. For my owne part I can beare all private and perſonall inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries;
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 12. Maſter <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughes,</hi> Maſter <hi>Goodwin, &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> and take <hi>pleaſure</hi> in <hi>reproaches</hi> for Chriſts ſake; I tooke it as a badge of honour to be abuſed among my <hi>betters;</hi> I wiſh I were their companion in abilities as I have beene in oppro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bries. Yet it ſeemed ſtrange to me when Maſter <hi>Edwards</hi> told me that he neither knew me nor <hi>Foord</hi> that ſent the Letter, and yet that he ſhould publiſh it; for though he feekes a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble evaſion, I cannot excuſe him of raſh and unrighteous judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Firſt, he ſaith he had a ſecond letter from <hi>S. F.</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme what he wrote in the firſt, and much more; <hi>ergò</hi> the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment is <hi>Billa vera,</hi> and I am found guilty. If one witneſſe (ſpeaking twice) may goe for two,
<note place="margin">Si ſat ſit accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaſſe quis erit innocens.</note> 'tis time for every man to learne his <hi>Neck-verſe.</hi> But <hi>Verbum Sacerdotis</hi> is Logicke and Law enough for Canoniſts; though for my part I approve better of the Moraliſts, who will not take an aſperſion for a conviction. The Scribes and Phariſees ſaid once and againe that Chriſt blaſpheamed;
<note place="margin">Mat. 9.8.</note> was it therefore true? the poore multitude and common ſort of people glorifie God for that which the Scribes accounted blaſpheamy.
<note place="margin">Rapiunt ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti coelum, &amp;c.</note> Wiſe men often times come ſhort of what ſimple ones attaine unto. God will have more praiſe from Babes then the wiſe and prudent of the world. Againe, he ſaid the Letter was brought to him by an Aſſembly-man of whom I told you before: if he had call'd him a Prophet, or one of the Sonnes of the Prophets, or a Man
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113788:6"/>of God, or a Maſter in Iſraell, he might have paſt for as good an <hi>Oracle</hi> as they have at <hi>Poole;</hi> this would have ſtrucke the naiſe to the head indeed; eſpecially if he had ſate in the chaire of <hi>infallibillity</hi> that day that he might not have <hi>err'd</hi> in what he did. But can you thinke a man of that <hi>gravity</hi> ſhould be ſo <hi>light</hi> as to be blowne from <hi>Ludgate-hill</hi> to Maſter <hi>Edwards</hi> his houſe with one paper-puffe of falſe fame? I doubt there's <hi>hem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke</hi> in the <hi>Synods</hi> garden; though perhaps you might thinke there were no <hi>weedes</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi> But grant that ſuch a one did deliver me up to Maſter <hi>Edwards</hi> to be crucified in my good name and credit; doth he deſerve to be judge that will proceed without a jury? I ſuppoſe the ſcroule which the <hi>Synod man Received</hi> and delivered contained onely the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, not the <hi>Affidavit</hi> of <hi>S. F.</hi> and therefore was no legall teſtimony againſt me: but righ or wrong in my name muſt to the blacke bill. I am perſwaded I ſhould have found more favour from an Heathen; if <hi>Pilate</hi> himſelfe had beene my judge he would have asked <hi>what evill I had done;</hi> &amp; heard me ſpeak, and my witneſſes too, (though ſuborned ones) before he had paſt ſentence on me: many times there is more juſtice and mercy in Civill, then in Eccleſiaſticall Courts. <hi>Pilate</hi> had relea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Chriſt and never ſtretched out his hand againſt him if the cheife Preiſts and Elders had not ſate ſo neare to jogge his El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow <hi>Luk:</hi> 23.4, 5. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 23.</note> there be ſome Divines ſo farre tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed into the deity of the God Saturne that they cannot in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to behold their owne iſſue, but devour their off-ſpring as ſoone as it ſhootes forth: though a man be borne in a <hi>Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Church</hi> (if there be any ſuch now) and received as a <hi>mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> by that which ſome call baptiſme, and never <hi>cut off</hi> by ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of excommunication; yet if he but preach and practiſe <hi>that doctrine</hi> which <hi>that Church</hi> profeſſeth to maintaine, for all that he were better fly into <hi>Aegypt</hi> then tarry in <hi>Judea:</hi> the Apoſtles had better entertainement amongſt the Gentles then amongſt the <hi>Jewes.</hi> Chriſt had a ſafer protection under <hi>Pharoah</hi> then under <hi>Herod;</hi> the children of the <hi>Spirit</hi> were better expoſe themſelves to meere ſtrangers and Aliens then to thoſe that are borne but after the <hi>fleſh;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 4.29.</note> and ſafer will it be
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113788:7"/>(for the outward man) to live amongſt Publicans and Sinners then amongſt devour Jewes; for if the Rulers of the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue, the Parſon of the Pariſh &amp;c. cannot intangle and quell them,
<note place="margin">Fo. 19.12.15.</note> the Civill Magiſtrate ſhall have little reſt till a Crowne of <hi>Thornes</hi> be on their heads. What elſe is the meaning of whetting the ſecular ſword ſo ſharpe with <hi>Gangraenous</hi> Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles to the Parliament and higher powers to ſuppreſſe <hi>ſome</hi> which worſhip God after that way which <hi>others</hi> (onely) call, but not prove to be Hereſie?</p>
            <p>I will now give over wreſtling I was never brought up to theſe <hi>Olympian</hi> games, nor do I delight in ſuch exerciſes, though ſome make them their recreation. But <hi>David</hi> may take his <hi>ſling</hi> in hand as well as his <hi>ſheepe crooke;</hi> he may fight with a <hi>Philiſtine</hi> as well as feede his Fathers Ewes: becauſe I am forc'd rather then come upon the ſtage, give me leave to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend my ſelfe from <hi>Rabſhekah's</hi> pen, and <hi>Goliah's</hi> beame: you will not blame the peaceable and quiet traveller for uſing his weapon and crying <hi>Theeves, Theeves,</hi> when he is ſet upon in the way and like to be over-maſter'd by men-ſtealers,
<note place="margin">Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſemel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſa poſtea nullus eris.</note> who would robb him of his good name, without which a man is no man; the modeſteſt damſell will lift up her voice when vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence is offered to her virginity, nor can I with ſilence, let paſſe theſe mendacious ſlanders which impetuouſly attempt to raviſh the purity and ſimplicity of the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>Methinkes theſe preſent times correſpond much with the former and give a cleare interpretation of many paſſages in ſcripture. You know when Chriſt was borne, not only <hi>Herod,</hi> but all Jeruſalem was troubled at it, and when he comes it is to kindle a fire, to ſend a ſword, to ſet at variance &amp;c. And though the Temple of Jeruſalem was built without the noyſe of an <hi>Axe</hi> or <hi>Hammer</hi> in it, 1 Kings 6.7. Yet the walls of that Citye were repaired in <hi>troblous tymes;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 9.25.</note> when the workemen wrought with one hand,
<note place="margin">Neh. 4.17.</note> and held their weapon in the other. He that will worke for God had neede be arm'd againſt men. I will hold thee no longer, though I intended once to have examined the libellous letter of <hi>S.F.</hi> a litle more narrowly before thee; yet I ſhall reſt, and deſire thee to be ſatisfied for
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113788:7"/>the preſent with what my borther will ſay concerneing it in his Narrative. I could ſpeake enough of all my defamers, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>heare ſay</hi> to make them odious; but then I ſhou'd doe as I have bin done by, and not as I would be done by, and want proofe, it may be, as well as they. I ſee there is falſhoode in fame; I wonder wiſe men ſhould give heede to ſuch lying va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nityes. As for that blackemouth'd booke which keeps ſuch a ſnarling at the Saints I turne my back upon it; not for feare to flee from it, but in diſdaine and ſcorne of it; For
<q>Major ſum quam cuipoſſit Gangraena nocere.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I truſt to weare ſuch armour of proofe alwayes upon me that will defend backe and belly from the inſolent thruſts of infernall forgeryes;
<note place="margin">Integer vitae ſceleriſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> purus non eget Mauri jaculis.</note> and therefore ſhall caſt off all other har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and appeare noe more in Roman buffe in this quarrell; <hi>Sauls</hi> armour ſits not eaſye on me: my doctrine and converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall be the ſheild and buckler of my reputation. I had been ſilent ſtill, but <hi>Codrus</hi> his bawling will break the ſtring of <hi>Aegles</hi> his tongue; too much foule play will make a dumbe man ſpeake: nothinge but that provok'd the pen of him who was unwillinge to write, but is ready to ſerve thee in the Goſpel of Chriſt</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Auguſt</hi> 18 1646.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Henry Pinnell.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="narrative">
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:113788:8"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Narrative of</hi> Iohn Maddockes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt I came to <hi>Poole</hi> (in my way to <hi>Weymouth,</hi> and other Weſterne places) where ſtaying a little time, I had one day ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with Maſter <hi>Bromhill</hi> (riding from <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne</hi> to <hi>Poole</hi>) wherein we did concurre without any difference at all, Maſter <hi>Bromhill</hi> deſiring and engaging me to farther acquaintance; after which (upon a Saterday) I viſiting him at his quarters, we fell into a diſcourſe, wherein I lovingly and freely gave a full accompt of my judgement, he aſſenting to every thing that I ſaid ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting ſome little difference concerning the exerciſe of a mans gifts without an externall call; wherein he ſaid he was not fully ſatisfied in every particular in his owne judgement, yet objecting otherwiſe no errour in my judgement, he invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Enſigne <hi>Taylor</hi> (who was going away) to ſtay and heare what diſcourſe we had, and what he ſaid to me, which was expreſly to this purpoſe (both in matter and expreſſion) if not verbatim, and as orderly placed here, as ſpoken by him.</p>
            <p>Sir, I finde you a man Orthodox and right in your judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and I would to God you could ſtay in this Towne, it might be a great means to prevent errours amongſt this people, and ſo long as it is you with them, in Gods name meet as often as you will, and I would to God all the Lords people were Prophets, and though I am not in my own judgement wholly ſatisfied concerning preaching without a call, yet finding you ſuch a man as you are, if you are ſatisfied in it your ſelfe, doe as you will, and I ſhall begrutch the opportunities that I am not with you; whereupon I deſired him to be with us the next day, and to aſſiſt us in our communion together; he ſaid his time would not then permit, but deſired that we might a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113788:8"/>time have a meeting together of the Chriſtians in the Towne, wherein each might freely declare himſelfe in love to other, for the uniting themſelves faſter together in the bond of love.</p>
            <p>At one meeting I was preſent, wherein there was abundance of love profeſſed, and nothing more long'd for by us then the performance of the promiſes then made; afterwards in my ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence they had (it ſeemes) another meeting or two, where Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>S. F.</hi> ſaith they did all (at leaſt in appearance) punctually agree, by which parentheſis (compared with conſequences) is ſuſpected, that ſome were preſent, who were ſomething in appearance, towards the Chriſtians in the Towne, that they were not in heart.</p>
            <p>After my returne from <hi>Weymouth</hi> we had a meeting on the fifth of <hi>September,</hi> 1645. wherein Maſter <hi>S. F.</hi> with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of his brethren, propounded a Queſtion, which was it ſeemes the maine thing ſtickled at, and propounded by them the firſt meeting, but deferred till then upon ſome conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. The Queſtion was, viz.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> Whether a man out of office, or without an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward call (having onely the name of a brother) may in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſpeech vent his owne thoughts upon a place of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, before thoſe to whom he ſtands no otherwiſe related? To which, Maſter <hi>Bromhill,</hi> with the approbation of the reſt of his brethren (to wit, Maſter <hi>S. Foord,</hi> Maſter <hi>Welſteede,</hi> Maſter <hi>Throttle,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Huſſey</hi>) in the firſt place premiſed two things in diſlike of the affirmative.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that the originall of that opinion were Anabaptiſts, Socinians, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that the Parliament and State were againſt it, and then gave his reaſons for his judgement againſt it, to which the reſt of his brethren agreed. After all which, I being deſired to ſpeake my judgement in it, (I deſiring, and they all promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, that in caſe we did not fully agree in our judgement, we ſhould notwithſtanding preſerve a Chriſtian love and unity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether according to their former profeſſion.)</p>
            <p>I began lovingly and freely to declare the Reaſons of my
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113788:9"/>diſſent from their judgement, which you ſhall have here ſet downe with this relation, more orderly then could there be permitted, but the ſame things exactly.</p>
            <p>After the handling (as I may ſo call it) in reſpect of the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdities and paſſion there vented) of ſome parts and peices of the arguments propounded, it was not denied, that ſuch a pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice is diſcovered in the Scripture, but not in ſuch times as theſe, the Church being then in perſecution: it being next de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded what other rule we have to walke by then they had, (an injunction being on them and us to take heed to the moſt ſure word of the Prophets) and where, in the Scripture, the warrantableneſſe of that practice is prohibited: with other paſſages that are too large, and not my intention here to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularize; Maſter <hi>S. F.</hi> anſwered that it might be lawfull to doe it in the North, in <hi>Wales,</hi> or other darke places, where no Miniſters are, but it ought not to be done in a place where a Miniſter is, without his tryall and approbation, ſo not denying it to be lawfull in it ſelfe, and preſidented in the Scripture, but altogether unlawfull, without that conſideration; then after demanding whether Chriſtians ſhould neglect their duty (held forth in the Scripture) in caſe a Miniſter is ſo reſolute as not to yeild to it, though a good thing? I replyed, that I needed not to plead the lawfulneſſe or unlawfulneſſe of that, for I had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away that objection by my practice; in diſcourſing firſt with Maſter <hi>Bromhill,</hi> declaring his words (as before) in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of me, that I was Orthodox, &amp;c. (which words of his, it ſeemes they were ignorant of) at which the objection being clearely fruſtrated, they ſtood all ſilent, looking upon Maſter <hi>Bromhill</hi> for his anſwer, who ſtood up, to mine and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers admiration, and called the Living God to witneſſe, that he never ſpake it to me; to which I replyed before the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple (which I ſuppoſe to be 200 at leaſt) that I wondred he had the face to deny that which was ſo publickely ſpoken, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore foure or five witneſſes, one of which (by name Enſigne <hi>Taylor,</hi> a very godly man, and well approved of by Maſter <hi>Bromhill</hi> himſelfe) preſently came before all the people, and witneſſed to the truth of it, rehearſing the ſame words of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113788:9"/>
               <hi>Bromhill's</hi> approbation of me, at which Maſter <hi>Bromhill's</hi> ſtood up haſtily with a bluſhing countenance, and made no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther anſwer but this; What doe you meane to doe? doe you meane to ſhame me before the people? if you ſhame me I will ſhame ſome of you; to which the witneſſe replyed thus; ſhame you Sir, or ſhame you not, you did ſay ſo, and I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der you can deny it, After which, (Objections being ſo clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly removed) I immediately appealed to themſelves whether they had any accuſation againſt me either in Judgement or pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice; ingeniouſly declaring what our practice was, and how our communion together was mannaged; which was not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly evident to the people themſelves, (our meetings being as publique as poſſible could be) 1. That no place might be left for an objection of doing any thing that we had cauſe to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of, and likewiſe a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for the ſatisfaction of thoſe, who through reports and calumnies of malicious ſpirits, were feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full that we did ſome ſtrange and ridiculous things, yet taking the opportunity of a free liberty (apprehended by our carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age) to behold our practices, and be amongſt us, they condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned their owne ignorance and folly in beleiving thoſe things, for which there was not a ſeeming ground. I ſay that the truth of what I declared concerning our meetings, and the manner of our communion together, was not onely evident to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by beholding our practices, but alſo Maſter <hi>Throttle,</hi> (one of the Miniſters, ſometimes a Captaine in the Parliament (ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice) acknowledged preſently that he had the notes of what was ſaid and done, yet not endeavouring the leaſt exception againſt it; All which being ſo, that no roome was left but for a reſolved ſupremacy (as if it had beene deſigned to inſnare me) ſtormes of paſſionate accuſations began to ariſe, which preſently vaniſhed, and were not able to laſt; Maſter <hi>Throttle</hi> affirmed, that I was an Anabapriſt (as he cals it) which was ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally knowne where my ſelfe was knowne, to be contrary to my judgement: and I had (not long before) diſcourſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it; nay I preſume he knew me to be otherwiſe minded; and I asking his reaſon for what he ſaid, he anſwered, becauſe I held ſomething which they hold; by which rule, every Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113788:10"/>in <hi>England</hi> may be proved a Papiſt, for holding ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that the Papiſts hold; preſently upon that he affirmed boldly that I had ſaid (there preſent) that there is no Church in <hi>England,</hi> infomuch that I was conſtrained to deſire him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geniouſly and modeſtly to give me ſatisfaction, by acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging his errour preſently, for the people did generally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie the contrary; and not onely ſo, but Maſter <hi>S. F.</hi> alſo witneſſed with them preſently, the falſhood of his accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Then Maſter <hi>S. F.</hi> (more ingenuouſly) endeavoured to try me with an interrogatory, <hi>viz.</hi> whether I beleived in my conſcience that Maſter <hi>Bromhill</hi> was the Paſtor of that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation? to which I replyed, that though I would not (by ſuch a deſired power) be put upon interrogatories, and give my owne judgement in it, yet I would tell him, what Maſter <hi>Bromhills</hi> owne expreſſions were to me of his judgement in it. <hi>(viz.)</hi> That when I ſaid to him ſat the forenamed diſcourſe, which we had at Major <hi>William Skuts</hi> houſe) that I conceived he would not ſo owne himſelfe Paſtor of that place, as to take the whole Towne as a Church, to whom he ſtood ſo related: he (ſhrinking at it) ſaid theſe words; no I confeſſe I ſhould be loath to doe ſo; and though no errour could appeare to be vented in our communion together, our diſcourſes and exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes being alwayes ſpent to edification of each other, in truths that are not diſputable, which I ſuppoſe none will contradict, or if occaſion be, will not be aſhamed of publique view; yet Maſter <hi>S.F.</hi> paſſionately affirmed, that ſuch private preaching (as he termed it) was the occaſion of all the errours now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad; to which I replyed, that it cannot be ſo, nor his aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion true; for before private meetings were ſo common as now, we had ſo many errours broached in the Pulpits, as hath cauſed 3 or 4 yeares ſitting of the Synod to diſcover, and it is not therefore erroneous, becauſe private or publique; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques will broach and vent errours in either; nay not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo, but that I had alſo heard errours preached in their pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, for one came up and bad the people pray, repent, &amp;c. and therein they ſhould doe God a courteſy; another bad them plow up the fallow ground of their hearts, and ſave God a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113788:10"/>which I there told them, I hoped none of them would juſtifie, but rather acknowledge to be fundamentall errours. The men that delivered it were Maſter <hi>Hall</hi> (lately gone from thence to <hi>Chicheſter</hi>) and Maſter <hi>Welſtoede</hi> (the Lectarer) who was preſent at this diſcourſe, and as none in his behalfe juſtified what he had thus delivered as Orthodox, ſo himſelfe denied not the words.</p>
            <p>Then Maſter <hi>Bromhill</hi> began to ſpeake in this manner to the people; You ſee (but with which eye none could tell) Maſter <hi>Maddockes</hi> his arguments are confuted, will not hold, &amp;c. I replying thus; Gentlemen, it is not your votes of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation will ſerve, but it muſt be done by Scripture, and you and I are parties, not competent judges in the buſineſſe; let thoſe that know Jeſus Chriſt, and have heard what hath beene ſaid, ſpeake what weight they conceive to be in your argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments or mine; Maſter <hi>S.F.</hi> preſently began to goe (as he cals it) Parliament way, dividing the houſe (which was indeed a convention of all ſorts of people in the Towne) deſiring them that were for me to ſtand to one ſide, and thoſe that were for them to the other ſide, as if there were an intention to make a diviſion of ſides in the Garriſon; I then de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing the people to ſtand ſtill in their places, lovingly asked Maſter <hi>S.F.</hi> it they would vote the Goſpell by multitudes, or rather (as before propounded) aske their judgements, of whom we had expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience to be godly (they onely being meet to judge) and that though (as I told him) I looked not on himſelfe, and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of them, in that notion of the multitude (he taking of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence at that expreſſion) yet I appealed to him, and the reſt, what the Scripture ſpeakes of the major part of the world, which indeed by and by appeared; for when they did notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding divide, (which was it ſeemes the hopefull cord to hold when the reſt were broken) and had made up their ſide, one of that ſide did pawne her little faith by ſwearing aloud that there was a baſe come off, others railed, that are not able to give a reaſon (<hi>pro</hi> or <hi>con</hi>) for ſcarce any thing of their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion. This is knowne to all and the Miniſters were deſired immediately to obſerve it, ſo that this conſidered, I conceive
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113788:11"/>all will judge it to be as much as is any where heard of, that in nigh 250. there ſhould be by his owne confeſſion in his Letter,) nigh 40 knowing Chriſtians; one in 5 is more then one of a City, and two of a tribe; yet I ſuppoſe Maſter <hi>S. F.</hi> himſelf knowes he ſpeaketh the leaſt of one ſide, and to the moſt on the other, which I ſhall let paſſe, it being ſo invalid a conſideration; and I ſhall appeale to Maſter <hi>S. F.</hi> with all that were preſent, whether their judgement or mine were beſt approved by the major part of thoſe that ſpake; or whether any thing conſiderable (in their owne apprehenſions) was ſpoken in the behalfe of their arguments, but by one Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Sprint,</hi> (a godly man) who had, not three dayes before, ſpake to me contradictory in private, which I there before them, told him of, and he then alſo profeſſed himſelfe unſetled in his judgement, but deſiring information in it, and hath ſince come to me, declaring the grounded diſſent ſupon ſerious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration) in his judgement to theirs, and that little which himſelfe had ſaid in the behalfe of it, adding, that he is ſo farre convinced, that if occaſion were he would freely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare his judgment againſt it in publique. And for the reſt which Maſter <hi>S. F.</hi> calls my Proſelytes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I ſhall leave him to reckon with Ieſus Chriſt for calling his Diſciples my Proſelytes, no ſmall affront to their Lord and Maſter.</p>
            <p>I ſuppoſe Maſter <hi>S. F.</hi> cannot name one, that did fall off from that meaſure which they did before profeſſe to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, nor prove that the number of thoſe that did thus walke in communion together, are ſince abated one.</p>
            <p>So when all this would not ſerve (the deſigne being, it ſeemes, either to over-power or daunt us, though the righteous are bold as a Lyon) Maſter <hi>Throttle</hi> paſſionately threatned to take courſe with me another time, whereupon I deſired him preſently, if he knew any errour in my judgement to accuſe me with it before the people, that they might not be deceived, or if I had offended againſt the Lawes, to procure an examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion preſently by Maſter Mayor (who was newly gone thence) or ſome other Iuſtice of the peace, and I would not refuſe any
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113788:11"/>puniſhment which the Law inflicts. It not being faire, ſo to pretend an abortive accuſation before ſo many people, as if ſomething extraordinary were amiſſe, and then (probably) acquit me in private before two or three perſons; to which he anſwered, that he would doe it when the Governour came home; and asking him if the weapons of his warfare were carnall, he anſwered, that ſome were, reſolving (it ſeemes) that what could not be done by ſpirituall weapons, ſhould (if it could) by carnall.</p>
            <p>Thus I have as briefly as I can conveniently (and I am ſure as truly as can be done) according to my friends deſire, in ſome meaſure I hope ſatisfied thoſe, whoſe cares have all moſt ting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led (and I can ſcarce blame them, when (conſider the artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall pretences of thoſe gifted tongues, that are ſo eminently inſpired by an ambitious ſpirit) at the very name of ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and ſuch a meeting, which never appeared to them, but in the monſtrous ſhape of maliciouſly diſguiſed ſtories; and alſo fully anſwered the deſires of thoſe, who have beene eye-witneſſes of my converſation, have had an account of my Judgement, and yet could ſcarce chooſe but wonder, what thoſe acclamations meant, that have ſo often beene made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind my backe: nay ſome have divers times ſince heard a ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification of my ſelfe and others to our faces publiſhed by ſome of the Grandees of our accuſers; yea the ſame partie, have heard both the deſperate ſlanders and accuſations behind my backe, and after that, the juſtification to my face, by one and the ſame mouth; what all this meanes, I leave to ingenuous people to judge, hoping that it will not be offenſive to any ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious perſon, that being ſo put upon it (unleſſe my owne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence ſhould ſpeake the guiltleſſe, guilty) he who hath ſo long (contentedly) undergone the calumnies and reproaches of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and malice, (tho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ugh never juſtified face to face) doth now at laſt onely relate the truth, which will upon examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be found exactly as it is here reported.</p>
            <p>So I conclude this, and in the next place crave leave to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve foure or five things in the honeſt Gentlemans letter,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113788:12"/>wherein I conceive will appeare, ſome contradictions or mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes, whether weake or wilfull, I will not determine.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He ſaith in the beginning of his Letter, that they were much infected with Antinomi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n errours; and yet after ſaith, that when they came to diſcourſe together, they did all punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally agree.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He ſaith they were wonne into errour, by the preaching of grace and juſtification; and adds, that they endeavoured to winne them out by the ſame meanes; neceſſarily implying, that the doctrine of grace and juſtification winnes both into errour and truth; contrary to 2 <hi>Tit.</hi> 11.12.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He ſaith they call grace and juſtification, and that onely, the preaching of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>To which I muſt ſpeake my knowledge, that if he meanes all the doctrine of grace, as well the foundation, as the right building upon that foundation, then its truth, but if he meanes that they account nothing but the laying of the Foundation to be a preaching of Chriſt, then its a great injury to them. For though I cannot ſay that I am in every circumſtance of ſome of their judgements, (which can I ſuppoſe ſcarcely be ſaid of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Chriſtians in any part of the Kingdome, though agreeing in Fundamentals, nay and in the maine of diſcipline alſo; which likewiſe we finde frequent in the Scriptures, eating and not cating, regarding and not regarding of a day, &amp;c. yet I know that they account the preaching of duties to be the preaching of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Obſerve his Parentheſis (that Maſter <hi>Pinnell</hi> might as well have charged the Holy Ghoſt with weakeneſſe as <hi>Paul</hi>) which I leave to Maſter <hi>Pinnell</hi> and all judicious Chriſtians to conſider of.</p>
            <p n="5">5. He ſaith that becauſe enough was not allowed to thoſe bare revelations, they had prepared an argument (as they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived) without exception, <hi>viz.</hi> their oracle, a ſupernumerary Sybill at leaſt, whoſe extaſies they much confided in; To this I muſt needs ſay, that I conceive Maſter <hi>S. F.</hi> to exceed the bounds of Chriſtian modeſty, in calling a diſtracted woman the Saints oracle (for ſuch I am confident he conceives them) and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113788:12"/>ſhall leave him to another reekoning with their Lord and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter for that; and likewiſe my ſelfe beard the invitation of Maſter <hi>S. F.</hi> and his brethren, to ſee the woman, wherein did appeare onely ſome kind of admiration at her condition and expreſſions, with a deſire of their viſit, hoping for aſſiſtance to her by it. After which its moſt probable that ſome diſcourſe was of Revelations, and what God could doe, to the end that the diſcoveries of Gods ſpirit to his people, (which ſpirit re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veales all that the Saints know of God, though never contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictory to his word) ſhould not be ſo reproached as too fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently it is. But to my knowledge it was ſo generally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived amongſt them that ſhe was diſtracted, that my undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed confidence is, ſhe was no oracle of theirs (whoſe oracle I preſume is the Spirit and word of God) nor in their apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions a ſupernumerary Sybill; though a Chriſtians being in ſuch a caſe, may poſſibly cauſe (not a little) admiration in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. And for their labouring to conceale it by intreaties and pretences; I appeale to any, whether more appeared then a deſire that ignorant people, and enemies to Chriſt, and the Saints, might not if poſſible take occaſion by her diſtraction which was hoped to be but ſhort, &amp; now I heare is in a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure paſt) as uſually they doe in ſuch caſes, to attribute the Saints afflictions to profeſſion of religion.</p>
            <p>In the next and laſt place, I ſhall give a true account of the Queſtion propounded, and the arguments for the affirmative, which (upon their deſire) were propounded by me, with ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry little, if any addition, and as exactly as poſſible in the ſame tearmes, with the maine objections there made againſt them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> Whether a man out of office (or without an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward call) having onely the name of a brother, may in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſpeech vent his owne thoughts upon a place of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, before thoſe to whom he ſtands no otherwiſe rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Affirmative.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Its a duty required in the Scripture, without reſtriction to length of time, or number of perſons, 3 <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. exhort one
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113788:13"/>nother daily, whiles it is called to day. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.10. every man, as a ſteward of the manifold grace of God, which he hath received, muſt miniſter the ſame to others, and the rule is, as he hath received the gift. 12 <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. Having then gifts dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering (according to the grace that is given us) whether pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy, let us prophecy, or an office, let us waite upon our of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, whereas there is a diſtinction made betweene an office, and prophecying, ſo both muſt be done according to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of faith, as in the 7 verſe.</p>
            <p>More fully, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.1, 3, 4, 5, 6, 30, 31, 39. in the firſt verſe is an expreſſe command to endeavour after (for the Churches good) the gift of prophecy, and in the third verſe is an expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of prophecy, he that prophecyeth ſpeaketh unto men to edification, exhortation, and comfort, and in the fourth and fifth he wiſheth that they did alſo prophecy, that they might edifie the Church; So in the twelfth verſe, ſeeke that ye may excell to the edifying of the Church; and in the twenty fourth and twenty fifth verſes, implying prophecy to be, the Saints ſpeaking out the experiences of their owne ſoules, he ſaith, that thereby the ſecrets of unbeleivers hearts are made manifeſt; ſince as face anſwereth face in the water, ſo anſwereth the heart of man to man; but farther in the twenty ſixth verſe, he ſaith every one of them hath ſome gift or other, a Pſalme a Doctrine, an interpretation (which is ſuppoſed to be of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture) a revelation; all which he exhorts them to uſe in the Church, and for the Churches edification. This he ſpeakes to the whole Church, verſe 23. and in 30.31. verſes; if any one (without exception) hath any thing for edification revealed to him, the Spirit of God is not to be quenched in him, the firſt is to hold his peace, according to that in the 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.19. 20. quench not the ſpirit, deſpiſe not prophecying; and then its added, for ye may all prophecy one by one, that all may learne and all may be comforted; which as it forbids the quenching of the ſpirit, ſo it anſwers an objection that might be then, and is now made, againſt the ſpeaking or prophecying of inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our gifted Saints, and thoſe that are looked upon as weake ones; in which anſwer is conteined two reaſons why ſuch
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:113788:13"/>ſhould not behindered, 2. that all may learne, (Gifts and Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents increaſing by Uſury 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Mat.</hi>) 2. that they might all be comforted, by the growth and increaſe of gifts and graces in the Church, it being the ſpirituall diſpoſition in a Saint, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in the increaſe, that is of God though in another.</p>
            <p>Two <hi>Objections</hi> were made againſt the premiſes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Object: That by Prophets is there meant onely Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in Office; and that the word (all) hath reference only to Prophets ſo taken: To this the Anſwer is three folde.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That were ſuperfluous, for it was never queſtioned whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men in Officiall authority might exerciſe their guifts.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If only thoſe are there meant, then of neceſſity, there muſt be at leaſt 5 or 6 prophets or miniſters in Office, in one Church (for the Apoſtle ſpeakes of ſuch a particular Church as might come together, (the whole Church) at one time, and in one place) there might three ſpeake; and there muſt be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, (the reſt) to judge, againſt which is the practiſe of the objections, who rather would have one officer to two Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, ſpeaking at will, as an infallible Oratour, or divine Oracle, and none muſt judge, ſo that (if it be ſo) they have at leaſt changed the Ordinances &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Apoſtle layeth downe the reſtriction 34, 35. verſes to be onely of women, which muſt be in oppoſition to men, not to prophets, let your women keepe ſilence in the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, for it is not permitted unto them to ſpeake, implying clearely, that it is permitted to men, and no ſhame for any but women, to ſpeake in the Church.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Second Objection was, that this would breed a great confuſion; for all to ſpeake.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw:</hi> 1. all cannot ſpeake, becauſe all are not gifted.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If all could, and were ſo gifted, yet the Ordinance of God breedes, no confuſion, or as the Holy Ghoſt anſwereth the objection (32, 33. verſes) God is not the author of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, but of peace, as it all Churches of the Saints, and the ſpirits of the Prophets are Subject to the Prophets that is (I conceive) one will not confuſedly contend with another, but freely give way, (to thoſe that are moſt able) for the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:113788:14"/>edification, according to that rule in the 26. verſe, <hi>Lor all things be done to edifying:</hi> Againe, though all have liberty and may (ſeaſonably and without confuſion) ſpeake or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie, it doth not therefore neceſſarily follow, that every member muſt ſpeake ſomething every time that the Church it come together; ſuch a conceipt were abſurd, all things muſt be done to edification.</p>
            <p>Thus for anſwer to thoſe two objections, then obſerve farther, that in the 37. verſe, the Apoſtle layeth downe this on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as neceſſarie, to a man that thinks himſelfe a prophet or Spirituall, let him (ſaith he) acknowledge the things which I write unto you to be the commandements of the Lord, let him be rightly principled in the doctrine of the Goſpell, and in the 39.40. verſes he concludes thus; wherefore brethren covet to prophecy, and forbid not to ſpeake with tongues; hinder not the exerciſe of any guilt which God hath given to the Church. Yet in the 40. verſe, let all be done decently and in order; ſo that all the gifts given to the Church may be uſed in the Church, without confuſion, the ſpirits of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets being ſubject to the Prophets, verſe 31, 32, 33.</p>
            <p>But if any man (ſaith he) be ignorant, let him be ignorant, verſe 28.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Argument in drawne from the example of the Saints in Scripture, 8 <hi>Acts,</hi> 4.11. <hi>ch.</hi> 19.20. 8 <hi>chap.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> verſe, note that all were feattered except the Apoſtles; and 4 verſe, they that were ſcattered went every where preaching the word. So 11 <hi>chap</hi> 19, 20. they that were ſcattered upon the perſecution that aroſe about <hi>Stephen</hi> (ſome were men of <hi>Ciprus, &amp;c.</hi>) preached the Lord Jeſus both to Iewes and Grecians. 21 verſe, the hand of the Lord was with them, and a great number beleived and turned unto the Lord; and in 22 verſe, when tidings came to the Church at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> they ſent <hi>Barnah as</hi> to aſſiſt them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who when he was come, and had ſeene the grace of God, was glad, and exhorted them, &amp;c. he never queſtioned their call to it: ſo in the 1 <hi>Phil.</hi> 14, 15. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking of his bonds, and the things happened to him, that they were fallen out to the ſut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance of the Goſpell, he ſaith in the 14 verſe, that many of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:113788:14"/>the brethren in the Lord, (which is the denomination of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry member) waning confident by his bonds, were much more bold to ſpeake the word without feare; and in 15, 16, 17, 18. ſome (he ſaith) did preach Chriſt out of envy and ſtrife, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing to adde afflictions to his bonds, yet he rejoiced that Chriſt was preached by them; though it be altogether im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable, that they would ordeine ſuch to office, whoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions were to adde afflictions to <hi>Paul's</hi> bonds; for we find them very carefull of ordeining any that were not ſoundly tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and <hi>Paul</hi> charging <hi>Timothy</hi> to lay hands ſuddainly on no man; not doe I remember mention or complaint made of any ſuch Officers in any of the Churches at that time.</p>
            <p>Another proofe is in the 18 <hi>Acts,</hi> 24.5, 6, 7, 8. where we find that <hi>Apollos</hi> was inſtructed onely in the baptiſme of <hi>John</hi> therefore not (in the leaſt meaſure) probable to be called to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice in the Church by any of the Apoſtles, when ſo ignorant of the way of God and the Churches walkings, yet he taught di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently the things of the Lord, and ſpake boldly in the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue, and after (onely) a more full information in the way of God, by <hi>Aquila</hi> and <hi>Priſcilla,</hi> he mightily helped thoſe that had believed through grace, convincing the Iewes, and that publickely, that Jeſus was Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Argument is drawne from the nature of faith it ſelfe, which is, to ſpeake what it hath ſeene and heard, ſo the Apoſtles <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi> and <hi>John</hi> argued. 4 <hi>Acts,</hi> 20. being threatned by the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell and Preiſts, and charged to ſpeake no more in the name of the Lord Jeſus, the reaſon which they gave why they muſt ſpeake, was not drawne from any officiall authority, but from the working nature of faith in them; we cannot (ſay they) but ſpeake the things which we have ſeene and heard. And in the 116 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10. I did believe, ſaith <hi>David,</hi> therefore have I ſpoken. So in the 66 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26. being experienced in the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God delivering him; as he ſaith in another place, the word did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in his breaſt, ſo here, he could not reſerve in his owne breaſt what God had done for him; Come hither (<hi>ſaith he</hi>) all ye that feare the Lord, &amp; I will tell you what he hath done for my ſoule. So in the 32 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.5. I acknowledged my tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:113788:15"/>(ſaith he) and thou forgaveſt my iniquity, well in the 5 verſe. For this ſhall every one that is godly pray unto thee in a time when thou mayeſt be found; implying that he would not be ſilent, but ſpread Gods name of pardoning iniquity, tranſgreſſion, and ſinne, which he had experience of, as an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to others, to expect the ſame which he had found; ſo 40 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8, 9, 10. and in the 23 <hi>Jer.</hi> the Lord con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnes them as falſe Prophets, that ſpeake when he hath not ſpoken to them.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Argument is drawne from the end of God in giving of gifts: 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.7. The Apoſtle having aſſerted in the fourth verſe that the Saints gifts, of what meaſure and kind ſoever of which he nominates divers, 8, 9, 10, 11, verſes, are by the ſelfe ſame ſpirit of God; he concludes in the 7 verſe, but the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of the ſpirit is given to every man to profit withall. And in the 5 <hi>Mathew,</hi> 14. Chriſt to the Diſciples ſpeakes of it, as the end of God in making them lights, that they might ſhine, and as an abſurdity to Reaſon it ſelfe, a thing which no man will doe, to put a light candle under a buſhell, where no man ſhall have the benefit of it.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Argument: it is no where (in Scripture) contradicted, but often encouraged and commended; 11 <hi>Numbers,</hi> 26.7. <hi>Eldad</hi> and <hi>Medad</hi> prophecyed in the campe; <hi>Joſhua</hi> complaining to <hi>Moſes</hi> of their preaching; Envyeſt thou (ſaith <hi>Moſes</hi>) for my ſake, I would to God all the Lords people were Prophets.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> Againſt this was objected by Maſter <hi>S. F. Moſes</hi> wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that they were all Prophets, but not that they ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy before they were Prophets.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. None can prophecy before they are gifted and enabled to it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It cannot have reference to an outward call, but to that which was the objection, <hi>viz. Eldad</hi> and <hi>Medad</hi> (who were not of the Preiſthood) prophecying by the ſpirit of God, and <hi>Moſes</hi> wiſh had beene very ſuperfluous, if when they were thus prophets, they ſhould not prophecy.</p>
            <p>Againe in the 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.19. quench not the ſpirit, deſpiſe not prophecying: ſo that where the ſpirit of God is, it ought not
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:113788:15"/>to be quenched, nor prophecying by it; but the ſpirit of God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s in many Chriſtians out of office, therefore not to be quench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed &amp;c. and Chriſt reprooves the Diſciples, for forbidding the man that caſt out Divells in his name, and tells them, that no man that doth a miracle in his name, can lightly ſpeak evill of hime ſo likewiſe in the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. Chap. 1, 3, 4, 5, <hi>v.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtle deſiring that they might not be ignorant con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſpirituall gifts, and ſpeaking of the diverſities of ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations and adminiſtrations from the ſame Lord, and the ſame Spirit, he ſaith in the third verſe, that he gives this to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by the Saints, that no man ſpeaking by the ſpirit of God, can call Ieſus accurſed; the ſpirit of God cannot poſſibly diſhonour Ieſus Chriſt, and no man can ſay, that Ieſus is the Lord (no man can truly exalt Ieſus Chriſt) but by the Holy Ghoſt: ſo in the 12 of <hi>Mathew</hi> Chriſt having (by the ſpirit of God) caſt out a Divell, the Phariſes accuſed him (blaſpheming the ſpirit of God) of caſting out Divells by <hi>Beelzebub</hi> the Prince of the Divells, now obſerve Chriſts anſwer, in juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of any thing done by the ſpirit of God, after his convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of them by their own children, and the impoſſibility of a houſe ſtanding which is divided: againſt it ſelfe, he ſaith in the 28 verſe, if I caſt out Divells by the ſpirit of God, then the Kingdome of God is come unto you; and in the third verſe he that is not with me is againſt me, he that gathereth not with me ſcattereth abroad (now gathering muſt be by exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on &amp;c. and the Scripture reſtraines not to method or forme in it) and farther its added in the next verſe (as a check or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe of thoſe that undervalue and ſlight the Spirit of God) wherefore I ſay unto you, all manner of ſinne and blaſphemy ſhall be forgiven unto men, but the blaſphemy againſt the Holy Ghoſt ſhall never be forgiven, and whoſoever ſhall ſpeak a word againſt the ſonne of man &amp;c. intimating the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full quenching &amp; deſpiſing of the ſpirit of God, to be a ſinne of the higheſt nature, or as <hi>Marke</hi> hath it, brings in danger of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall damnation, becauſe they ſaid he hath an uncleane ſpirit.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Argument:</hi> Thoſe that haue not improved their Talents by gathering with Ieſus Chriſt, have been ſentenced and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:113788:16"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Mathew,</hi> 23. he that had but one talent, and kept it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a napkin, is accounted an unprofitable ſervant, and bound hand and foot and caſt into outer darkneſſe, and in the aforenamed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Mathew,</hi> he that gathereth not ſcattereth abroad.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Argument:</hi> That which is eſpecially authorized a Call in Scripture, is a ſending and enabling by the Spirit of God to Preach the word of God.</p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. compare with the 23 <hi>Ieremiah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>enes:</hi> how ſhall he preach except he be ſent, it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies that if he be ſent he can Preach, yet many of thoſe that have been ſent with the outward call pleaded for, could never Preach the glad tydings of the Goſpell of Peace; which <hi>ſent ones</hi> are there ſpoken of, with reference to the Peoples be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving upon the diſcovery of the Goſpells glad tidings by them: compare with it the 23 <hi>Ier.</hi> 21. I have not (ſaith God) ſent theſe Prophets yet they ranne, which ſending is expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the latter part of the verſe, I have not ſpoken to them yet they Prophecyed. So in the 16. verſe. they ſpeake a viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their own heart, and not out of the mouth of the Lord ſaying they ſhall have peace &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Yet theſe in the 13 and 14 verſes, were Prophets of <hi>Sana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> and Prophets of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> (outwardly called) and in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> verſe the Lord ſaith expreſly, that if they had ſtood in his Counſell, and cauſed his people to heare his words, a bleſſing ſhould have attended their Miniſtry, they ſhould have turned them from their evill waies, and from the evill of their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</p>
            <p>It was there affirmed by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>S.F.</hi> that the Lords complaint here was, that they were not ſent with an outward call, which if they were not, then.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt it muſt be cleared, why they are called Prophets of <hi>Samaria,</hi> and Prophets of <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly it muſt neceſſarily follow, that God will bleſſe the endeavours of men, without an outward Call, which ſtand in his Councell, and Prench his word, and not the viſior of their own hearts verſe 22.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:113788:16"/>
            <p>I have now as briefly as I can, related the truth, not ſo much (if at all) for my own vindication, as for the Saints and the Goſpells ſake, both which have been ſo ſlandered and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermined by pretended Friends.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>In the Title page for <hi>Deſertè</hi> reade <hi>Diſerti.</hi> Pag. 4. lin. 24. for <hi>dealts</hi> r. <hi>deale.</hi> p 9. l. 11. for <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ame</hi> r. <hi>name.</hi> l. 15. for <hi>right. right.</hi> p. 11. l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. for <hi>borther</hi> r. <hi>brother.</hi> p. 18: Adde [2] to the beginning of l. 25. p. 19. l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>2. for <hi>never</hi> r. <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</hi> p. 22. l. 15. for <hi>Chriſtians</hi> r. <hi>Chriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There be many miſtakes in <hi>ſtops</hi> and <hi>points<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> which, being but <hi>Punctil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>'s</hi> of Grammar, and ſervants to vvaite upon an <hi>Emphaſis</hi> in Oratory, I have left (by reaſon of my abſence from the Preſſe) to exerciſe thy judgement and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
